<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: dungeon fodder | Jørgen's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="https://jorgen.tjer.no/blog/categories/dungeon-fodder/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://jorgen.tjer.no/"/>
  <updated>2023-09-03T15:43:56-07:00</updated>
  <id>https://jorgen.tjer.no/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jørgen Tjernø]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Announcing Arcane Deathmatch]]></title>
    <link href="https://jorgen.tjer.no/post/2012/09/09/announcing-arcane-deathmatch/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-09T15:10:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>https://jorgen.tjer.no/post/2012/09/09/announcing-arcane-deathmatch</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The last few months it&rsquo;s been busy with three weddings (including my own) and a vacation. Every once in a while I&rsquo;ve been tinkering with a game prototype with a smaller scope than Dungeon Fodder - and now I&rsquo;ve finally reached a point where I can say that I&rsquo;ll be pursuing this concept instead of Dungeon Fodder. I first had to make sure Unity&rsquo;s (fairly lacking) networking APIs would be suitable for developing this.</p>

<p>The game is tentatively named &ldquo;Arcane Deathmatch&rdquo;, and it&rsquo;s a third person / top down, fast paced, RPG-inspired multiplayer action game. The gameplay is similar to the Warcraft 3 custom map &ldquo;Warlocks&rdquo; (I think?): You control a wizard/warlock on a relatively small battlefield. You&rsquo;re pitted against a few adversaries, all of you armed with whatever spells you&rsquo;ve purchased. As you survive and kill off your opponents you&rsquo;re awarded gold with which to purchase new spells between rounds.</p>

<p>Every time you&rsquo;re hit by a spell, you lose some health and get knocked back. The less health you have, the easier you are to knock around. If you get knocked off the map, you&rsquo;ll probably sustain damage wading through a lava pit, be nibbled on by piranhas as you swim to shore, or fall off the map.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/early_adm.png"></p>

<p>So far, I&rsquo;ve got rudimentary networking and gameplay working - two or more players can connect to eachother and fight it out (armed with Magic Missile!), and getting knocked off the map means falling to your death. It doesn&rsquo;t look like much - but that&rsquo;s never stopped me before! ;-)</p>

<p>Vital things that are missing are more spells, rewards, a way to buy said spells, more interesting maps / terrain / obstacles, and a scoreboard. (Probably in that order)</p>

<p>I hope you&rsquo;ll follow my blog as I post status updates and my experiences developing this game :-)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lack of updates for a few weeks]]></title>
    <link href="https://jorgen.tjer.no/post/2012/06/18/lack-of-updates-for-a-few-weeks/"/>
    <updated>2012-06-18T12:41:38-07:00</updated>
    <id>https://jorgen.tjer.no/post/2012/06/18/lack-of-updates-for-a-few-weeks</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve attracted some people who are following the progress of this project, so I figured I should give a quick update on my (lack of) progress.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m in the middle of organizing a wedding reception, so there won&rsquo;t be any time for working on my projects until after the 26th of June. I look forward to getting back to it!</p>

<p>So far, updates have been on a weekly schedule. I intend to continue with that pace - or maybe biweekly, depending on how much time I have. Right before this lack of updates began, I started prototyping a game based on some of the same concepts, but with a smaller scope. I might pursue that so that I have a playable, &ldquo;done&rdquo; game at an earlier point. If so, it&rsquo;ll be featured in an upcoming post. :)</p>

<p>Thank you all for your feedback and interest! This is exactly why I publish this publicly!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Dungeon Fodder Update #7]]></title>
    <link href="https://jorgen.tjer.no/post/2012/05/28/dev-diary-007/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-28T16:59:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>https://jorgen.tjer.no/post/2012/05/28/dev-diary-007</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><div class="embed-video-container"><iframe src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/yX0M2LjnyOc" allowfullscreen></iframe></div></p>

<p>A little busy the past two weeks (Diablo 3 and a lot to do at work), but here&rsquo;s what I had time to do:</p>

<ul>
<li>Reworked minimap</li>
<li>Inventory management</li>
<li>New spell, &ldquo;Barrier&rdquo;</li>
<li>Non-active player switched to <a href="http://angryant.com/behave">Behave</a>-based AI - he now shoots at enemies!</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Inventory management]]></title>
    <link href="https://jorgen.tjer.no/post/2012/05/26/inventory-management/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-26T14:39:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>https://jorgen.tjer.no/post/2012/05/26/inventory-management</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I added some rudimentary (but functional) inventory management:</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://i.imgur.com/7nQjQ.gif">http://i.imgur.com/7nQjQ.gif</a>"></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Minimap cleanup]]></title>
    <link href="https://jorgen.tjer.no/post/2012/05/19/minimap-cleanup/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-19T13:58:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>https://jorgen.tjer.no/post/2012/05/19/minimap-cleanup</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Didn&rsquo;t get too much done this week, but I cleaned up the minimap:</p>

<p>Minimap before:<br/>
<img class="<a" src="href="http://i.imgur.com/0z7oB.png">http://i.imgur.com/0z7oB.png</a>" title="&ldquo;Minimap before&rdquo;" ></p>

<p>Minimap after:<br/>
<img class="<a" src="href="http://i.imgur.com/9wMdz.png">http://i.imgur.com/9wMdz.png</a>" title="&ldquo;Minimap after&rdquo;" ></p>

<p>I also added a dungeon level indicator:<br/>
<img class="<a" src="href="http://i.imgur.com/dXnTI.png">http://i.imgur.com/dXnTI.png</a>" title="&ldquo;Dungeon level indicator&rdquo;" ></p>

<p>And finally I switched the non-player character to use the same AI engine as the zombies (<a href="http://angryant.com/behave">AngryAnt&rsquo;s Behave</a>), though with a different behavior tree. So far this just means that the non-player character actually attacks enemies. Woo!</p>

<p>Hopefully I&rsquo;ll have time to make the inventory management more complete and do a dev diary this weekend. We&rsquo;ll see.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
