<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: playtesting | Jørgen's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="https://jorgen.tjer.no/blog/categories/playtesting/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://jorgen.tjer.no/"/>
  <updated>2023-10-01T15:17:11-07:00</updated>
  <id>https://jorgen.tjer.no/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jørgen Tjernø]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[First playtest of Arcane Deathmatch]]></title>
    <link href="https://jorgen.tjer.no/post/2012/10/06/first-playtest-of-arcane-deathmatch/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-06T15:24:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>https://jorgen.tjer.no/post/2012/10/06/first-playtest-of-arcane-deathmatch</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday I asked two coworkers to play Arcane Deathmatch with me, to get an initial feel for what direction I&rsquo;m going in. It was a great experience, and a great motivator: I finished up a large amount of basic implementations of features in the last week, so that it&rsquo;d be ready for the playtest.</p>

<p>I <strong>highly</strong> recommend doing this early for people working on hobby projects - it helps you focus on shipping and creating a real product, and motivate you. During the time leading up to the play-testing, I started thinking of every issue I&rsquo;ve filed in the bugtracker in terms of &ldquo;how important is this to testing gameplay&rdquo;.</p>

<p>Some very useful things I learned include:</p>

<ul>
<li>Controls need to be thought about very carefully, and tested on real people. What seems fine when you&rsquo;re just testing around the environment is experienced completely differently when you&rsquo;re in an action-packed fight.</li>
<li>While art is not important to the &ldquo;fun&rdquo; in this concept, UX is very important - even early on. People need to find the information and actions they care about!</li>
<li>Pacing is very important, and hard to get right - there are a <em>lot</em> of factors that influence it, many of which I haven&rsquo;t gotten around to implementing yet.</li>
</ul>


<p>There were a lot of other subtle bugs and improvements I found through this little hour of gameplay. As an example, camera movement is currently not animated, which makes Teleport <strong>very</strong> jarring.</p>

<p>For now, I&rsquo;m back to implementing some new content (especially a more interesting level and more spells) - and then I can get a better feel for how pacing and balancing needs to be done.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
